Guide to the Ruth Wilson Collection on Human Rights and Social Work TAM.342
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II: Affiliated Human Rights and Social Work Organizations, 1974-2005; 1985-2002; 10 Linear Feet in 14 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, and 2 oversized flat boxes
  - IFSW -- Guatemala -- Alex Mejia, 1994 (Box 58, Folder 7)
  - IFSW -- Human Rights Commission, 1989-1994 (Box 58, Folder 8, Box 59, Folder 1-3)
  - IFSW -- Newsletter, 1991-1994 (Box 59, Folder 4)
  - IFSW -- Policies, undated (Box 59, Folder 5)
  - IFSW -- Terry Bamford Human Rights Article, 1989 (Box 59, Folder 6)
  - International Korean Alliance for Peace and Democracy, 1994 (Box 59, Folder 8)
  - The Israeli Council for Israeli-Palestinian Peace (ICIPP), 1996 (Box 59, Folder 7)
  - Labor Party Advocates, 1994 (Box 59, Folder 9)
  - Lawyers Committee for Human Rights, 1987-1989 (Box 59, Folder 10)
  - National Association of Social Workers (NASW), 1988-2001 (Box 60, Box 61, Folder 1)
  - NASW -- Antiwar, 2001-2002 (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - NASW -- Bertha Capen Reynolds Video Project, 2001 (Box 61, Folder 3-4)
  - NASW -- "Bread, Not Bombs: A Role for Social Workers in the Peace Movement", 1983 (Box 61, Folder 5)
  - NASW -- Code of Ethics, 1996 (Box 61, Folder 6)
  - NASW -- Currents (Newsletter), 1989-2001 (Box 61, Folder 7-9, Box 62, Folder 1-2)
  - NASW -- Death Penalty, 1980 (Box 62, Folder 3)
  - NASW -- Election Materials, 1984-2000 (Box 62, Folder 4-6)
  - NASW -- Governor George Pataki 16-Point Declaration Plan, 1995 (Box 62, Folder 7)
  - NASW -- Healthcare Committee, 2000-2001 (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - NASW -- International Affairs Committee, 2000 (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - NASW -- International Development/Peace and Social Justice Course Reader, 1991 (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - NASW -- Jacqueline Steingold, 2002 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - NASW -- Meeting Materials, 2002 (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - NASW -- Membership List, 1989 (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - NASW -- Publications, 1993-1994 (Box 63, Folder 7)
  - NASW -- Social Workers and the Challenge of Violence Project, 1996 (Box 63, Folder 8)
  - NASW -- Social Workers for Peace and Justice (SWP&J), 1996 (Box 63, Folder 9-10)
  - NASW -- United States Chapters, 1988-1990 (Box 63, Folder 11, Box 88, Folder 4-5)
  - NASW -- World Assembly Conference, 1991-1992 (Box 64, Folder 1-2, Box 88, Folder 6)
  - Oxfam America - Tools for Peace and Justice, 1989 (Box 64, Folder 3, Box 88, Folder 7, Box Shared Tamiment 171, Folder 8)
  - Philippine Resource Center, 1985 (Box 64, Folder 4)
  - Physicians for Social Responsibility, 2002 (Box 64, Folder 5)
  - Same Boat Coalition, 1995-1997 (Box 64, Folder 6)
  - Union of Concerned Scientists, 2005 (Box 64, Folder 7)
  - United Nations, 1986-1995 (Box 64, Folder 8, Box 65)
  - United Nations -- Children's Rights, 1989-1993 (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - United Nations -- Chile, 1977 (Box 66, Folder 2)
  - United Nations -- Conventions, 1990-1992 (Box 66, Folder 3-6)
  - United Nations -- Economic and Social Council, 1989 (Box 66, Folder 7)
  - United Nations -- Janice Wood Wetzel, undated (Box 67, Folder 1)
  - United Nations -- South Africa and Apartheid, 1987-1991 (Box 67, Folder 2-3)
  - United Nations -- World Human Rights Conference, 1993 (Box 67, Folder 4-5)
  - United Nations -- Yugoslavia, 1991-1993 (Box 67, Folder 6)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, 1989 (Box 67, Folder 7)
  - Women's Organization for Political Prisoners (WOFPP), 1991-1992 (Box 67, Folder 8)
- Series III: Research Files, 1958-2004; 1990-2004; 12.54 Linear Feet in 18 manuscript boxes, 2 flat boxes, and 2 oversized flat boxes
  This series contains materials Ruth Wilson collected while researching specific countries including Chile and Puerto Rico, as well as the types of human rights violations occurring in those locations. It also contains topics files and research materials related to Ruth Wilson's other areas of interest such as women's rights, homelessness in the United States, American politics, the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT), the Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism (a subset of the Communist Party USA), the American healthcare system, domestic violence, Marxism, unions, the LGBTQIA community, racism, Native American rights, and discrimination. Subject files on individuals including Bertha Capen Reynolds, Karen Silkwood, Langston Hughes, Martin Luther King Jr., Madeleine Albright, and Rosa Parks can also be found within this series.
  Materials consist mainly of newspaper clippings, magazine clippings, journal articles, brochures, flyers, conference materials, posters, photographs, booklets, essays, and correspondence. It is possible that research materials in this series were used by CIHRI, however, there were no clear indications of this link within the individual research folders.
  Materials have been arranged alphabetically.
  - Affirmative Action, 2002 (Box 68, Folder 1)
  - American-Soviet Friendship, 1989 (Box 68, Folder 2)
  - Angela Davis Incarceration, 1971 (Box 68, Folder 3, Box 88, Folder 8)
  - "Anthem for a New Depression" Sheet Music, 1974 (Box 68, Folder 4)
  - Antiwar, 1991-2002 (Box 68, Folder 5-8, Box 69, Folder 1, Box 88, Folder 9)
  - Bertha Capen Reynolds, 1978, 1980, 2001 (Box 69, Folder 2, Box 88, Folder 10)
  - Breakthrough Magazine, 1992-1993 (Box 69, Folder 3)
  - Cambodia, 1993 (Box 69, Folder 4)
  - Chile, 1976-1983 (Box 69, Folder 5-6)
  - China, 1994 (Box 69, Folder 7)
  - Colombia, 2000 (Box 69, Folder 8)
  - Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism, 1990-2000 (Box 70, Folder Unknown, Box 71, Folder 1)
  - Communism, 1988-1991 (Box 71, Folder 2-4)
  - Communist Party Conference Materials, 1990-1991 (Box 71, Folder 5)
  - Conference -- Looking for Ways to End Violence, 2001 (Box 71, Folder 6)
  - Conference -- On the Future of the United States-Chile Relations, 1978 (Box 71, Folder 7)
  - Conference -- Socialist Scholars, 2002 (Box 71, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence -- Kenneth Neilson, 2001 (Box 72, Folder 1)
  - Cuba, 1996, 2002-2003 (Box 72, Folder 2)
  - Death Penalty, 1996, 2000 (Box 72, Folder 3)
  - Disability Rights, 2000-2004 (Box 72, Folder 4)
  - Discrimination, 2000 (Box 72, Folder 5-6)
  - Dred Scott Case, 2001 (Box 73, Folder 1)
  - Economics and Poverty, 1997, 2000-2002 (Box 73, Folder 2, Box 86, Folder 7)
  - Emergency Campaign to Save Human Services, 1982 (Box 73, Folder 3)
  - Environmentalism, 1993, 1999-2001 (Box 73, Folder 4)
  - Faith Based Social Service, 2000-2001 (Box 73, Folder 5)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), 1976-1990 (Box 73, Folder 6)
  - Foster Care, 1979 (Box 73, Folder 7)
  - Genetically Modified Food, 2000-2001 (Box 73, Folder 8)
  - Genocide, 2002 (Box 73, Folder 9)
  - Gray Panthers, 1993-1994 (Box 73, Folder 10)
  - Homelessness, 1999-2000 (Box 73, Folder 11)
  - Human Rights, 1988-1995 (Box 73, Folder 12, Box 74, Box 75, Folder 1)
  - Human Rights Education, 1982, 1992 (Box 75, Folder 2-4)
  - Immigration and Refugees, 1991-1993 (Box 75, Folder 5)
  - Israel and Palestine, 1990-1994 (Box 88, Folder 11)
  - Jobs for All, 1995 (Box 75, Folder 6)
  - John Ashcroft, 2002 (Box 75, Folder 7)
  - Karen Silkwood, 1978-1983 (Box 75, Folder 8)
  - Langston Hughes, 2001 (Box 75, Folder 9)
  - Left Green Network, 1992 (Box 76, Folder 1)
  - Letelier-Moffitt Memorial Human Rights Awards, 1993 (Box Shared Tamiment 171, Folder 9)
  - LGBTQIA, 2000-2003 (Box 76, Folder 2-4, Box 86, Folder 8, Box 88, Folder 12)
  - LGBTQIA -- Empire State Pride, 2000-2001 (Box 76, Folder 5)
  - LGBTQIA -- Rights, 2001 (Box 76, Folder 6)
  - LGBTQIA -- Senior Action in a Gay Environment (SAGE), 2000-2004 (Box 76, Folder 7-8)
  - Madeleine Albright, 1997 (Box 77, Folder 1)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr., 2000 (Box 77, Folder 2)
  - Marxism, 1997 (Box 77, Folder 3)
  - McCarran-Walter Act, 1992 (Box 77, Folder 4)
  - Mexico, 1993-1996 (Box 77, Folder 5)
  - Minimum Wage, 2001 (Box 77, Folder 6)
  - Mothers in Prison, Children in Crisis Campaign, 1996 (Box 77, Folder 7)
  - National Committee Against Repressive Legislation (NCARL), 1997-2001 (Box 77, Folder 8)
  - National Parks, 1999-2000 (Box 77, Folder 9)
  - "The National Security Strategy of the United States of America", 2002 (Box 77, Folder 10)
  - Native American Rights, 1992-1993 (Box 77, Folder 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) and General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT), 1992-1993 (Box 77, Folder 12, Box 78, Folder 1-4, Box 86, Folder 9, Box Shared Tamiment 084, Audiocassette 342.0004)
  - Oregon Right to Die Campaign, 2000 (Box 78, Folder 5)
  - Pacifica Foundation and WBAI, 1996 (Box 78, Folder 6)
  - Panama, 1993 (Box 78, Folder 7)
  - Patriot Act, 2000-2002 (Box 78, Folder 8, Box Shared Tamiment 171, Folder 10)
  - Pharmaceuticals, 2000 (Box 79, Folder 1)
  - Photograph - Ruth and Ted Wilson, undated (Box 79, Folder 2)
  - Police Brutality, undated (Box 79, Folder 3, Box 88, Folder 13)
  - Political Affairs - Journal of Marxist Thought, 1990-1991 (Box 79, Folder 4)
  - Political Prisoners, 1991-1992 (Box 79, Folder 5)
  - President Jimmy Carter and Nobel Peace Prize, 2002 (Box 79, Folder 6)
  - Public Citizen, 2001 (Box 79, Folder 7)
  - Puerto Rico -- Political Prisoners, 1999 (Box 79, Folder 8)
  - Racism and Reparations, 2000 (Box 79, Folder 9, Box 86, Folder 10)
  - Radiation Tests and Human Rights, 1993-1994 (Box 79, Folder 10)
  - Radical Women (Feminist Group), 1998-1999 (Box 79, Folder 11)
  - Rosa Parks, 2001 (Box 79, Folder 12)
  - Rosenberg Fund for Children, 2001 (Box 79, Folder 13)
  - RU486 (Abortion Pill), 2000 (Box 79, Folder 14)
  - Rwanda and Sudan, 1993-1994 (Box 79, Folder 15)
  - Social Work Ethics, 1980-1987 (Box 79, Folder 16)
  - Social Work in South America, 1985 (Box 80, Folder 1)
  - Social Work Theory and Education, 1976-2003 (Box 80, Folder 2-3)
  - Socialism, 2002 (Box 80, Folder 4)
  - Statue of Liberty, 1985-1989 (Box 80, Folder 5-6, Box 86, Folder 11, Box 88, Folder 14)
  - Sweatshops, 1994-2000 (Box 81, Folder 1, Box 86, Folder 12)
  - Torture, 1985 (Box 81, Folder 2)
  - Uganda, 1985 (Box 81, Folder 3)
  - Unions -- Committee for a Solid Contract, 1975 (Box 81, Folder 4, Box 86, Folder 13)
  - Unions -- Procedural Booklets, 1958-1970 (Box 81, Folder 5)
  - Unions -- Workers Rights, 1973-1975 (Box 81, Folder 6-7)
  - The Unionist - Official Publication of Social Service Employees Union, 1995 (Box 88, Folder 15)
  - United States Health Care Reform, 1992-1994 (Box 81, Folder 8, Box 82, Folder 1)
  - United States Politics, 1984-2004 (Box 82, Folder 2-5, Box 83, Box 84, Folder 1-4)
  - United States Welfare Reform, 1993, 1996 (Box 84, Folder 5)
  - Universal Declaration of Human Rights, 2004 (Box 84, Folder 6)
  - Verna Weed Collection for Progressive Social Work, 1989 (Box 84, Folder 7)
  - Vietnam, 1993-1994 (Box 84, Folder 8)
  - Vinegar Hill - Brooklyn, NY History, 1997 (Box 84, Folder 9)
  - Virginia McGuire Lerner, 2000 (Box 84, Folder 10)
  - Weeksville Society, 2000 (Box 84, Folder 11)
  - Women Fighting Poverty, 1993-1994 (Box 85, Folder 1)
  - Women's Rights, 1972-1974, 1992-2002 (Box 85, Folder 2-6)